in this section we're going to overview
the network core we're going to see what happens inside the network core and
we're going to introduce a number of
and we're going to introduce a number of
important topics we'll talk about backward forwarding packet queuing delays and packet loss we'll
talk about an alternative to packet switching known as circuit switching and we'll talk
about the structure of the internet we'll see what we mean when we say
the internet is a network of networks
the network core consists simply of a
set of routers that are interconnected
by a set
of communication links and the
internet's core operation is based on a
principle known as packet switching
which is really relatively simple the
idea is the following
what happens is that the end hosts that
we talked about earlier
take application level messages divide
those messages into chunks of data
put those chunks of data inside packets
and send those packets
into the internet now those packets are
then
forwarded along a path from a source
node
to a destination node for example from a
web server maybe to your laptop
that's running running a web browser
that made a request
from that web server so let's unpack
that last statement just a little bit
because we actually heard a lot of
important words there we talked about
forwarding
we talked about a path from source to
destination and we talked about a source
and a destination
there are two key functions performed
inside the network core
forwarding sometimes also known as
switching and routing
let's take a look inside a router so we
can see what these functions are
forwarding is a local action it's about
moving an arriving packet from the
router's input link
to the appropriate router output link
forwarding is controlled by a forwarding
table that we see here
and there's a forwarding table inside
each and every of the millions of
routers in the internet
when a packet arrives a router will look
inside the packet for a destination
address
and then look up the destination address
in its forwarding table as we see here
and then transmit that incoming packet
on the output link
that leads to that destination well
that's pretty simple conceptually
look up and forwarding but you might be
wondering
well how are the contents of that
forwarding table
created in the first place and that's
where we encounter the second key
function
of the network core and that's routing  is the global action of
routing is the global action of
determining the source to destination paths taken by packets as we'll see routing algorithms
compute these paths and compute the local per router forwarding tables needed to realize
this end-to-end forwarding path a good analogy for understanding the difference between forwarding and
routing is to think about taking a trip in a car i recently drove
from san jose california all the way to the east coast to northampton massachusetts
it was a long trip well i decided to take this upper route here
rather than this lower route here and
that's the routing decision
that's made the path that's taken from
the source
san jose california to the destination
northampton massachusetts
now when i get to an interchange say in
sacramento california
i'm coming into the city on one of the
input roads
and i need to be forwarded out of the
city on an
output road in cleveland here and really
at all intersections along the way
that switching from an input road to an
output road is the local
forwarding function with the global
routing function determining
which of the output roads i'm actually
forwarded onto
you might want to think just a bit about
this relationship between the local
forwarding function
and the global routing function can you
think of other analogies
let's next focus on the transmission of
packet bits at a router in the network
core
in this figure here we're illustrating
the bits in a packet being transmitted
from one router to the next
you'll hopefully recall that we said
that if a packet's
l bits long and the link transmission
rate is r bits per second
then it's going to take l divided by r
seconds to transmit the packet
into the link transmitted bits will be
received
and gathered up at the receiving end of
a link
until the full packet has been received
you can see the bits and the packets
being gathered up here
once the packet's been fully received it
can then be forwarded on to the next hop
and so on this is what's known as the
store and forward operation of a packet
switch network
now let's take a closer look at what
happens as packet arrived to a router
for forwarding
in this figure here we see a router with
three links
let's assume that host a is sending
packets to host c
and host b is sending packets to host e
and now let's take a close look at the
input link rates
the transmission rate r of the link from
a to the first hop router is 100
megabits per second
as is the second link from b to the
first hop router
but the transmission rate of the link
from the first hop router to the second
hop router is only 1.5 megabits per
second
it's almost 100 times slower and this
isn't far from the case in a home
network where the home network router
may have attached ethernets in the home
running at a gigabit per second or wi-fi
at 54 megabits per second
but the access link to the cable heading
is much slower perhaps only
5 or 10 megabits per second and so
here's the question
what happens as packets arrive to this
first hop router
well the router in this example can only
transmit at 1.5 megabits per second
and certainly packets can arrive a lot
faster than 1.5 megabits per second
if a and b are both transmitting a lot
of packets at the same time
if too many packets arrive at too fast a
rate then a queue of packets will form
in that first hop router
as shown in the figure queuing happens
whenever work arrives
faster than some service facility can
actually serve that work and of course
we're all familiar with queues here's a
queue of cars waiting to get service at
a toll booth
we wait in lines and stores at the
checkout counter
and i imagine many of you have been
waiting at lines in the bursar's office
to pay your bills
here's a group of people queuing to get
in a building and here's a group of
folks in the uk waiting
if you've been in the uk you probably
know that queuing is actually the word
that brits use to say when you're
waiting in line
the brits are really good at cueing
check out this video
this is the awfully thorough guide to
being
british governor call blimey
in this episode queuing
[Applause]
if queuing were an olympic event then
great britain would win
gold then it would wait for an hour take
a ticket
and win silver and bronze no one queues
better than the british
and if you want to fit in you need to
know the rules
well to get back to networking packet
cues are going to form at a router's outbound link whenever the arrival rate
in bits per second on the input link exceeds the transmission rate bits per
second of that output link for some period of time when there are packet
queues they're going to be queuing delays packets are going to have to wait
in routers rather than being forwarded on their way to their destination and because
there's only so much memory to store cued packets in a router the queue
becomes too long and a router's memory is exhausted an arriving packet may arrive
to a router and find no memory in which to be stored in such
cases a packet's going to be dropped or lost at that router and as
we'll see the fact that packets can be delayed and or lost is going
to be a major source of headaches for a lot of network protocols well
so far we've been talking about packet switching and we've just seen that packet
queuing delays and packet loss can happen because the network doesn't always control senders
carefully enough to ensure that large queuing delays and packet loss doesn't happen now
packet switching is not the only way to build a network and indeed long
before the internet was around and long before packet switching telephone networks employed a
different form of technology known as circuit switching let's take a look at circuit
switching in circuit switching there's a notion of a call rather than a notion
of packets that flow from source to destination before a call starts all of
the resources within the network that are going to be needed for that call
are allocated to that call from source
to destination
so once the call begins the call will
have reserved enough transmission
capacity
for itself to ensure that queuing will
never
occur there's no delay other than
propagation delay and
no loss of data within the network
because link capacity has been reserved
for the exclusive use of this call
in this diagram here each link has four
circuits
the call from the top left to the bottom
right is allocated the second circuit
on the top link and the first circuit on
the right link
the circuits are dedicated resources
they're not shared
with any other users it's really like
there's a wire
from source to destination so all this
sounds pretty good
no delays no loss doesn't get any better
than that
until you start to think about the fact
that since resources are reserved for
the exclusive use of a call
but the circuits can go idle if there's
no data to send on that call
and there's the rub if the bandwidth
isn't used by the call
it's lost no one else no other calls can
use it
and so a circuit switch network can be
inefficient as we'll see in a second
circuit switching is done in one of two
ways either
frequency division multiplexing fdm or
time division multiplexing tdm in fdm
the electromagnetic or optical spectrum
is divided into narrow frequency bands
and each call is allocated one of those
narrow bands
and can transmit at the full rate
allowed by that band
in tdm time is divided into slots and
each call is allocated a periodic set of
slots
a source can transmit only during its
allocated time slots but can do so
at the higher maximum rate of that wider
frequency band
so now that we've been introduced to the
notion of both circuit switching and
packet switching
let's take a look at a numerical example
to look at the numbers of users
that are supportable in a specific
networking scenario
here's the scenario we want to look at
let's assume that we've got a gigabit
per second link
there are end users and each of these
end users behaves as follows
when they have data to send they need to
send at
megabits per second that's one-tenth of
the overall link bandwidth
however users are only going to be busy
10 of the time that means 90 percent of
the time
they have no data to send let's take a
look at a numerical example
about how many packet-switched users and
how many circuit switch users can be
supported
in this network setting let's suppose
that n
is 35 users for the case of circuit
switching the calculation is easy
each user needs 100 megabits per second
under circuit switching
and so a circuit switch network can
support at most
10 users at a time now let's take a look
at packet switching
remember each user needs a hundred
megabits per second so we can support
10 packet switched users just like we
can support 10 circuit switch users
no problem but remember each user is
only busy 10 of the time what happens if
we allow
all 35 users into the system what's the
probability that more than 10 of these
are active
at a given time with more than 10 active
users
that's the only time queues are going to
form and grow
one can show with some basic probability
and combinatorics which are not required
for this class and so we won't go into
this calculation here
that the fraction of time that more than
10 of the 35 users are active
is point zero 0 0
4 that is if we let all 35 users into
the system under packet switching
then the percentage of time when queues
will start to grow
is less than four one hundredths of one
percent of the time
that's a pretty small number maybe we're
willing to put up with some
very occasional delay and loss in order
to allow
all 35 rather than just 10
users into the system this performance
gain under packet switching is known as
the statistical multiplexing gain
of packet switching and it was a key
argument for using packet switching
when packet switching was invented 60
years ago
it may seem to you now that packet
switching is just about the best thing
since sliced bread
is it a slam dunk winner it might seem
so
and even today's telephone networks
actually carry data
in packets these days so in some sense
we could declare
packet switching a winner package
switching is particularly great for
bursty data
when a source only occasionally has data
to send
it's simple there's no call setup
there's no resource reservation
a host just starts sending data that it
has to send
we've seen that congestion packet delay
and loss can happen
but we'll also see that internet
protocols tcp
in particular will react to congestion
by
decreasing the sender's sending rate in
the face of congestion
so congestion and loss can in some sense
be avoided or at least mitigated
is it possible to provide circuit-like
behavior with packet switching
well as the saying goes it's complicated
but we'll study various techniques that
try to be as circuit-like as possible
well let's wrap up our introduction to
the network core by coming back to a phrase that i've mentioned a couple
of times when i've said the internet as a network of networks what does
that really mean and how is that  actually reflected in the structure of  the internet
yikes it's like i'm stuck inside the
internet here well what we've seen so far is that the users at the
edge of the network are attached to access networks whether that be home networks
mobile networks institutional networks and some way we need a way to connect these
millions of access networks together to each other to get end to end paths
between users how might we do that well we could connect that is wire
each access isp to every other access isp but this would require order n
squared connections and when n is many millions this approach isn't going to scale
so given the millions of access isps we might create one global transit isp
each isp at the edge would then connect
to the global transit network
a backbone network if you will and one
access isp would reach another access
isp
through this backbone network and in the
early days of computer networking this
was indeed how
edge networks were interconnected to
each other
but of course if one global isp is a
viable business
they'll be competitors for backbone
network service and these global
backbone networks will need to be
interconnected to each other
we say that a network peers with another
network when they're directly
interconnected
the locations at which multiple networks
can peer with each other
are sometimes called internet exchange
points or peering points
regional networks might form
interconnect access network closer to
home
and also connect to the global backbone
in the state of new york
nisernet the new york state education
and research networks
is an example of a regional network that
provides internet access to universities
colleges museums
healthcare facilities and k-12 schools
and then content providers like google
or microsoft amazon akamai
might want to run their own global
networks which in fact they do
to bring their services and content
close to the end users
and this picture that we see here is
pretty close to the structure of today's
internet
we said that the internet is a network
of networks and now you've got a sense
of what that really means
at the center of the internet we have a
relatively small number of
well-connected
large networks these are sometimes
called tier 1
commercial isps such as level 3 sprint
at t ntt that have national and
international coverage
moving closer to the edge there are the
regional networks all of which
interconnect that's to say peer with
each other
and with tier one providers and at the
very edge of the network then
are the access networks themselves and
then of course there are the content
provider networks like google and
facebook
the private networks that connect their
data centers and services to the
internet
and sometimes bypassing tier one and
regional isps
and just to give you an idea of what a
tier 1 isp actually looks like
here's a recent map of sprint's u.s
network
you can see the various international
connections around the edge
each of these sprint nodes shown here is
actually a collection of routers
that together form a so-called point of
presence or a pop
here's a blow up of a pop where you can
see a set of links that connect
pop routers down to customer networks
another set of links that connect to
other sprint
pops and finally a set of routers that
connect to peering networks for example
other tier one networks well that
concludes our overview of the network
core and we've introduced a number of
really important concepts here
we talked about the packet forwarding
process we talked about
store and forward networks we talked
about queuing delays
the possibility for packet loss and we
distinguished between
packet forwarding and packet routing
we also talked about an alternative to
packet switch networks known as circuit
switch networks
and we talked about the pros and cons of
each and we finished up by talking about
well what we mean by that
concept of the internet being a network
of networks
coming up next we're going to take a  look at network performance